Markham Starr collection
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
- Series 5. 2020 accrual: Independent films, circa 2010 through 2019, afc2013031_dc005; 12 m2ts, 9 mp4, 8 m2t, and 1 txt
  - Clark Woodmansee: Life of a Dairyman, afc2013031_dc005; 1 m2ts (0:44:02)
    Clark Woodmansee, along with his son, operates a dairy farm in Preston, Connecticut. Clark narrates his family's history in the business, the daily operation of the farm, and the challenges they face as they struggle to keep alive in a world of corporations. Narrated against a backdrop of daily life on the farm.
  - David Gallop and the RI Engine Company, afc2013031_dc005; 1 mp4 (0:17:36)
    David and his brother Jay operate the RI Engine Company, started by their grandfather in 1947. It remains an essential operation for the fishermen of the port. David discusses the company history and what they do over scenes of the work being done at the business.
  - David Gallup and the Rhode Island Engine Company (longer version), afc2013031_dc005; 1 mp4 (0:24:40)
    This is a longer version of "David Gallop and the RI Engine Company" containing a little more information for historical purposes.
  - Gillnetting on the F/V Oceana, afc2013031_dc005; 1 m2ts (0:24:00)
    Dean Pesante describes his life in the fishery and how gillnetting works as a fishery. Narrated against a backdrop of a day-trip fishing out of the port.
  - Impressions From a Fishing Port, afc2013031_dc005; 1 m2ts (0:04:59)
    Video impressions of Point Judith set to music made for a general audience.
  - Jenn Fish: A Life in the Commercial Fisheries, afc2013031_dc005; 1 m2t (0:32:34)
    Jenn comes from a long line of fishermen, but is one of the few women fishing out of the port. Jenn discusses how she got into the fishery and the challenges she faces against the backdrop of a day's trip fishing for squid in Block Island Sound.
  - Joan Booth of The Bait Company, afc2013031_dc005; 1 m2t (0:14:40)
    Joan narrates what it is like to string bait for commercial lobstermen as an employee of The Bait Company.
  - Lobster Fishing on the Erica Knight, afc2013031_dc005; 1 mt2s (0:39:55)
    Mark Sweitzer discusses his unlikely path into the industry and how he fishes for lobsters in Rhode Island waters, set against a day's trip lobstering.
  - Lobster Fishing on the F/V Select, afc2013031_dc005; 1 mp4 (0:40:11)
    This film follows Rich Lodge as he fishes for lobster on a day trip off Block Island. Rich discusses all aspects of the business and his life in the fisheries.
  - Mark Sweitzer: A Life in the Lobster Fishery, afc2013031_dc005; 1 mp4 (0:10:51)
    A shortened version of "Lobster Fishing on the Erica Knight" - made for a general audience.
  - Martha Blackett of the Bait Company, afc2013031_dc005; 1 m2t (0:15:14)
    Martha narrates what it is like to string bait for commercial lobstermen as an employee of The Bait Company.
  - Mike Marchetti: The Waterman, afc2013031_dc005; 1 mp4 (0:13:01)
    A shortened version of "Scalloping on Point Judith Pond with Mike Marchetti" - made for a general audience.
  - Narragansett Bay Lobsters, Inc., afc2013031_dc005; 1 m2ts (0:22:33
    Documents the daily operations of a typical fish dealer situated right on the docks in Point Judith. Although they began as a lobster dealer, out of necessity, they have moved into the fish business as well. Narrated by Adam Morse, the owner, with scenes from daily operations behind his voice.
  - Oyster Farming on Point Judith Pond with Ian Campbell, afc2013031_dc005; 1 m2ts (0:23:10)
    Ian, along with his sister Stesha, started and run their own oyster farm. Ian narrates how he got into fishing to begin with and then into oystering with his sister. They discuss their methodologies, trials and tribulations in this business as they spend a day on the farm.
  - Oyster Farming on Point Judith Pond with Stesha Campbell, afc2013031_dc005; 1 m2ts (0:31:04)
    Stesha, along with her brother Ian, started and run their own oyster farm. Stesha narrates how she got into fishing to begin with and then into oystering with Ian. They discuss their methodologies, trials and tribulations in this business as they spend a day on the farm. Stesha is one of only a few women fishing out of Point Judith.
  - Pete Hanson: 53 Years a Machinist, afc2013031_dc005; 1 m2ts (0:17:07)
    Pete Hanson talks about his life as a machinist for the Rhode Island Engine Company, one of the most essential companies in Point Judith. Pete discusses evolution in equipment design and the work the company still does today. Background film is of Pete working in the shop.
  - Point Judith: Portraits From a Fishing Port, afc2013031_dc005; 1 mp4 (1:14:51)
    An overall look at Point Judith as a commercial fishing port - meant for a general audience.
  - Rodman Sykes: A Life in the Fisheries, afc2013031_dc005; 1 m2t (0:50:18)
    This film follows Rodman and his deckhand on a day trip as he narrates his families' history in the industry and his lifetime spent on the water. Rodman is one of the most highly respected fishermen in the port.
  - Scalloping on Point Judith Pond with Mike Marchetti, afc2013031_dc005; 1 m2ts (0:25:06)
    Mike discusses his life in commercial fishing as he fishes for bay scallops.
  - 6 Boats in 8.5 Minutes, afc2013031_dc005; 1 m2ts (0:08:42)
    This video was produced to run at a fishing festival and show the general public day trips on 6 different vessels involved in different fisheries- lobstering, squid fishing, scalloping, gillnetting, trawling for baitfish, and trapfishing. Silent film.
  - Stesha, afc2013031_dc005; 1 mp4 (0:03:59)
    This short film was made to help promote women in the commercial fishing industry. Stesha Campbell discusses how she got into commercial fishing and what she likes about the work.
  - Stesha Campbell: Learning the Ropes, afc2013031_dc005; 1 m2t (0:24:48)
    Stesha Campbell began her fishing career when asked by her brother if she would like to take a vacated position on the fishing vessel North Star. She began working on the floating fish traps with no prior fishing experience, and went on further to help her brother with his new venture in farming shellfish on Point Judith bay. Stesha narrates this film and discusses learning the business from scratch.
  - The RI Engine Company, afc2013031_dc005; 1 m2ts (0:16:32)
    Jay Gallup and his brother David operate the RI Engine Company, started by their grandfather in 1947. It remains an essential operation for the fishermen of the port. In this version Jay Gallup discusses the company history and what they do over scenes of the work being done at the business.
  - Trap Fishing on the Buckeye, afc2013031_dc005; 1 mp4 (0:04:15)
    A quick video of a trip to empty floating trap sites at Point Judith, RI. Ian and his sister Stesha Campbell bought some of Tom Hoxsie's trap sites as Tom became seriously ill with cancer and Ian did not want to see these historic sites disappear forever. This film has no narration.
  - Trawlworks, afc2013031_dc005; 1 m2t (0:31:57)
    Trawlworks builds and sells gear to commercial fishermen out of Point Judith. This film is narrated by several of the primary workers as they go about building nets for trawling. One of two companies in the area, they are essential to the operation of the port.
  - Wayne Gaumond: 32 Years Lumping, afc2013031_dc005; 1 m2ts (0:18:23)
    Wayne has been employed for most of his working life as a lumper in Point Judith. Lumpers unload fish from ships docked in the port, removing as much as 100,000 pounds per boat. Wayne discusses his work against a backdrop of him unloading the catch in the hold of the trawler Hopefull.
- Series 6. Published Materials, 2010-2015
  Series is print copies of four of Starr's books. Starr donated these books to the American Folklife Center at the same time as his other donations. Digital copies and drafts of some of these titles can be found in series 1 through series 5.
  Books are listed in alphabetical order.
  - Down on the Farm: The Last Dairy Farms of North Stonington, November 2010 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Finest Kind: The Lobstermen of Corea, Portrait of a Down East Fishing Village, 2011 (Box-folder 1/2)
  - In History's Wake: The Last Trap Fishermen of Rhode Island, 2015 (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Swab Summer: Transformation at the United States Coast Guard Academy, October 2013 (Box-folder 1/4)
Bibliography
Published works in this collection
Starr has compiled and edited some of the documentary works in this collection into published books (some of which are included in this collection, or have a draft version in the collection). The books directly related to material in this collection that have separate catalog records are:
Starr, Markham. Against the Tide: The Commercial Fishermen of Point Judith. North Stonington, CT: Fowler Road Press, 2009. A digital copy of this title is also part of this collection.
Starr, Markham. Down On The Farm: The Last Dairy Farms of North Stonington. North Stonington, CT: Fowler Road Press, 2010. Both a digital and a physical copy of this title are also part of this collection.
Starr, Markham. End of the Line: Closing the Last Sardine Cannery in America. Middletown, CT: Wesleyan University Press, 2013. A digital draft version of this title is also part of this collection.
Starr, Markham. In History's Wake: The Last Trap Fishermen of Rhode Island. North Stonington, CT: Fowler Road Press, 2010. Both a digital and a physical copy of this title are also part of this collection.
Other related publications
An additional documentary monograph by Starr which contains work not present in this collection is:
Starr, Markham. Barns of Connecticut. Middletown, CT: Wesleyan University Press, 2013.